All the music featured in this video is
original and I've uploaded the three
best tracks to Spotify, YouTube Music,
Amazon Music, Apple Music, all the rest
under the name Microbyte. I couldn't get
Mike Boyd, so go check it out. It's
Microbyte.
I have a serious case of gear
acquisition syndrome. So, ever since I
was a teenager, which was a while ago, I
have been collecting music gizmos and
hoarding them, never getting rid of
anything. And it's gotten kind out of
hand.
I have a bunch of synthesizers. I have
this Arturia Minibrute, this Behringer
Neutron analog synth, Behringer Model D,
the original Novation Circuit, cheap
Fender Squier, old Yamaha acoustic,
we've got Ibanez, Fender Telecaster,
nylon string guitar, steel string
guitar, rubber guitar, banjo, mandolin,
another banjo, mandolin, bamboo
saxophone, custom Warmoth guitar,
Takamine acoustic, Washburn SG-2000, G&L
2000, Orange Tiny Terror, and a Blues
Junior, Laney 15-W, Vox AC5, Peavey
50-W, Vox AC15, Mesa Boogie, Ableton
controller, [music] mixers, guitar
pedal, multitrack recorder, audio
interfaces, another Focusrite audio
interface, 88-key MIDI keyboard, 49-key
MIDI controller, Ableton Push
controller, another MIDI controller, KRK
studio monitors, two RE20 microphones,
and there's a whole bunch of that I
can't find right now, but it is out of
control.
Since I've been collecting all this
stuff, I have never, not once,
finished a piece of music, finished a
song, uploaded it anywhere, showed it to
anyone. I've just been messing around
for like 20 years. All I've done is just
make hundreds and hundreds and hundreds
of little ideas that I've recorded or
written down somewhere that haven't
amounted to anything. And that's kind of
sad. This is a hobby that I really,
really love, but I've never actually
made any music and released it to the
world. So, So, the aim. I want to write,
record, produce, and release just three
songs and release them on Spotify, Apple
Music, iTunes, YouTube Music, all the
rest. Not an album, not an EP, just
three finished tracks. In addition to
that, I'd like for every single sound,
every piece of music in this video, in
addition to the three tracks I want to
release, to be produced and made by me.
So, I wonder how long is that going to
take?
As always, this is day one, hour zero.
Right. First things first, I need to set
up my little studio up here in my attic.
>> [music]
[music]
>> This is going to be the center of my
music production, [music]
my base, if you like. And it's all built
around my new desk from FlexiSpot,
[music]
this week's sponsor of the show. When
I'm trying to make music, I'm constantly
[music] switching between different
things, sitting down for editing and
mixing, standing up to play guitar or
keyboard or bass, a lot of moving
around. So, I really needed a standing
desk with motors that could adapt to all
of [music] that for me. This is the
FlexiSpot E7 Plus, and it has a memory
function, so [music] I can save
different heights for different parts of
the process. I can have one height for
sitting and editing, another [music] for
playing guitar, and another for
keyboard, and then switch between them
at the press of a button. I went for
this massive 160 by 80 cm solid oak top,
which gives me loads of space while also
being incredibly sturdy and wobble-free.
And obviously, with all the equipment on
the desk, it can actually get pretty
heavy, but [music] with the E7 Plus,
which has a dynamic load capacity of 200
kg,
>> [music]
>> is extremely stable thanks to its
four-legged design,
that's not going to be an issue.
Thing I hate the most is wobble, and
there's no wobble.
>> [music]
>> Solid.
There are loads of options from
FlexiSpot, too. So, you can get a
smaller desktop [music] if you're
working with less space. Choose from a
range of different desktop materials.
There are two-legged versions, and some
models even have built-in storage.
[music]
And this one right here comes with a
10-year guarantee. In August, FlexiSpot
are celebrating their 10-year
anniversary with some amazing offers.
[music] They have a flash sale on the
31st of August, where you can get 12%
off sitewide with the code ENUK12.
And if you're interested in my [music]
desk, you can get an extra 40 pounds or
50 bucks off the E7 Plus using these
codes on screen now. Check out the deals
[music] through my link below in the
description. Thanks to FlexiSpot for
supporting the channel.
Let's make some tunes.
All right, welcome to my little stew.
Uh I have a very very basic setup that
took absolutely ages to to set up, but
we are here. So, right now, I am um
I'm running Ableton here. So, uh this is
my DAW of choice, which basically just
means
my music production software. I've tried
a bunch of other ones. This is the only
one that actually really really works
for me. It works fantastic. And um what
I've got here is a bunch of uh kit.
We have the laptop that's controlling
everything.
Uh
but this here is a controller for
Ableton. So, I can control basically
almost every function in Ableton that I
would like to control through this
device here. This is called uh
Ableton Push.
Um so, right now I have a grand piano
loaded up.
>> [music]
>> And then, just with push of a button, I
can load up a a drum set.
>> [music]
>> If I move over here,
what I have is a couple of hard couple
of hardware things. So, it's an Arturia
MiniFreak, which is a fantastic hardware
synthesizer.
>> [music]
>> This device over here is a Behringer
Neutron
a hardware synth. This is an analog
synthesizer
um and it only makes one note at a time.
It's a monophonic synthesizer, but it's
really really fat and well, it's analog,
so it's cool, right? And this red box
over here allows me to record audio into
the computer. So, I can plug in that
hardware synth or I can plug in this
microphone here or I can even plug um
guitar and bass into it as well. So,
basically this setup right here is a
really really basic home studio setup
and you can record synth drums, hardware
synths, guitars, vocals, whatever you
like just with this setup. It might It
might not be the most professional, but
you can get your sounds into the
computer and that's what's important. I
really I really don't [music] have any
excuse. I have everything I need to make
some music bar talent.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, as I explained, I've been messing
about with music stuff for years and
years and years and just never actually
made anything or really finished
anything or finished anything. That is
the problem. As a result, I have lots
and lots, hundreds of little snippets of
ideas that just haven't gone anywhere.
Just a couple of chords here and there
or a little melody or a drum beat or
something like that that I haven't done
anything with. So, I think a reasonable
place to start is to go through some of
those ideas, pick out ones that are
potentially good and try and develop
those. So, here's some that I've got.
Let's see how I'm getting on. So, I'm
just going to play these.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Well, that's
this
that's not very good.
>> [music]
>> I mean
I mean, it's like it's okay, but I don't
it's kind of cheesy.
>> [music]
[laughter]
>> Next.
That's not even it's not even music.
>> [music]
>> What we have here is like hundreds and
hundreds of projects of just really,
really crap music, crap ideas. And I
think that that is okay.
I think I've come up with like a couple
of good ideas in the last two decades.
But, if I remember correctly, it's
always been like 50 really crappy ideas
for one half-decent one.
And I think that is a case of just
churning out lots and lots of ideas and
playing around a lot until you come up
with something that's actually good and
worth working on. So, I don't mind
listening to a lot of crap here because
hopefully there's a couple of good ones
in there.
All right, I called this one run for
some reason and I think this one has
promise. Let me play what I've got so
far.
>> [music]
>> I think that little melody there has
promise. You know, some drums and some
bass, a couple of ABC sections. I think
we could work with that. Let's Let's
stick that in the working progress
group. By the way, if you are interested
in making your own music and you've
never done it before, trust me,
just give it a go. Even if you've never
touched an instrument or you have no
idea about bars and loops and chords
[music] and progressions and melodies
and harmonies, forget about all that.
Just get started, you'll pick it up on
the way, trust me. So, download either
Ableton Live Lite and [music] or Ableton
Live as a trial and start playing
around. And the only other piece of kit
you need is one of these. This is a MIDI
controller. Don't get too bogged down
about it. It's a controller for
controlling external instruments,
computer or otherwise. You just need a
cheap computer,
a free version of Ableton and a MIDI
controller.
>> [music]
>> Get on the tutorials, trust me, you'll
be making loops and beats and melodies
in no time. It is really easy to do.
No doubt what you make initially will
[music] be crap, but it will be unique
and yours. Don't do AI crap music, make
your own stuff. It's not that hard. So,
I've got this really, really simple,
basic melody that I've got that I've
got. It's just made up with two grand
pianos panned left and right.
So, it gives us a [music] really nice,
gentle, airy, sort of a
spacious feel to it. And there's a
little B section as well.
It works really [music] nicely.
However, I don't actually want it to be
pianos. I'm kind of going for more of an
electronic feel here. What I'd like it
to be is like synthesizers.
What I'm going to do is I'm just going
to replace both the pianos here with a
synthesizer and just play around with it
until I get something that I like.
That's way too low.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, I've played around for quite a long
time, actually. So, here's what I've
changed it for. Remember, it was piano
before. This is what it sounds like now.
>> [music]
>> So, quite a soft, airy, spacious feeling
sound. Pan left and right. Lots of with
lots of reverb.
>> [music]
>> That's kind of what I was going for.
That sounds quite nice. And I've got
this B section here.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, really, really simple. Nothing
complicated at all. Um and there's an A,
a B, and A section. So, next I need to
pad this out a little bit with some
drums, some bass, and maybe some other
instruments to to sort of start fleshing
out this this melody idea that I've got.
So, first thing I'm going to do, I think
it needs some drums. In my head, uh
although this is electronic, I kind of
want like a really dry like
quite a muted, understated drum kit. I
don't want like
So, what I'm going to do is just simply
browse through Ableton's uh drum kits
that they've got for me.
>> [music]
>> So, I'm not really looking for
uh like a a drum machine here. That's
quite nice.
>> [music]
>> Let's try the Let's try this one.
>> Okay, after a lot of after a while, and
I mean a lot, I'm so bad at programming
drums. Played a little bit and then
edited it by MIDI.
>> [music]
>> Turn it up a little bit so you can hear.
Stafford lay better than what I played a
little bit.
There you go.
Even if you're hopeless at finger
drumming on a pad like that, I can just
program like the basic like kick and
snare that I like and a little bit of
hi-hats. Then from there, I can really
start tightening it up with the mouse.
Right, that's the drums. Let's get some
bass. I just think I was just going to
go for like really simple octaves like
>> [music]
>> My timing is bad. It's bad.
>> Yeah, it's kind of filling out the
bottom end quite nicely without being
like too aggressive. Let's move on.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, I've just been messing around and
actually written something new.
>> [music]
>> I got this really cool bassline
that I've got this like bass guitar
plug-in.
>> [music]
>> Gives you like a sort of flea chili
peppers bass. [music]
And I just was playing around with it
and I came up with these like almost
like piano style chords but on a bass
guitar. Really cool. Quickly recorded
them, messed about tightened it up a
bit. So, we got this.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Really nice interesting bassline.
For the drums, I wanted to just keep it
really really simple, really loud,
really in your face.
Recorded like four bars on Ableton Push
cuz I like playing on the pads. When you
put them together, it sounds really
really cool. Listen to this.
>> [music]
[music]
>> And what I really thought would be
interesting here was be to to do like a
DJ Shadow style
um
glitchy drums where you kind of chop up
the drum audio and move it around in a
way that you wouldn't naturally play the
drums. So, it's really quite glitchy and
jerky. I really like that stuff. Um but
let's give it a try. So, uh here here's
my Here's some audio of my drums. And if
we just take a listen.
Just a straight
two-bar drumbeat.
I'm just going to literally
chop parts out
and just like copy and paste them in.
Let's do
Let's So, let's just see what this
sounds like.
>> [music]
>> So, that didn't sound very good.
[music]
>> All right, I've been doing a lot
chopping up of audio and uh we have a
bunch of cuts here. So, if I just play
uh from here.
>> [music]
>> I really like the sound of that. So,
let's have a listen to all those cuts
that I've made, those glitches I made
with the bass.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I think that sounds pretty cool. I mean,
it's kind of like Chili's and DJ Shadow
fused together and some into something
that's worse than both of them, but
pretty cool.
All right, melody. So, I am not going to
pretend that I have just come up with
this melody here. I've been here for
absolutely hours writing the most simple
melody ever. I'm just playing it on the
piano.
Um, this is what it sounds like.
I know that that melody is like as
simple as it could get, but that that
process takes me a long long time to do
that to write that. It's a lot of going
like
no,
>> [music]
>> no.
Yes. Okay, I've got that bit and then
working from there. So, it's really
really slow. I quite enjoy it, but it is
not a fast process writing music. But,
what I think I really need is a
different instrument here. What about a
really nice jazzy muted trumpet? So,
I've got a sample library here.
Let's have a listen to the trumpet.
>> [music]
>> Yes, that's more like it. That sounds
[music] great.
>> [music]
>> I think that will do for that first
melody part. I think I have a really
nice cello that would go here. That
would be nice.
>> [music]
>> Oh, that is [music] instantly lush.
Listen to that.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I don't think that needs any more work.
That that just that that the cello is
just the instrument to use there.
Fantastic.
So, I've been thinking a little bit
about why it's taken me so long to
actually do this, to make some music and
release it. And I don't think the
difficult part is I mean, it's hard to
make music, but I don't think that's the
the bottleneck for me. I think the
bottleneck is is, you know, fear of
what people are going to think or say
about the music that I make.
If you think about how much music you
actually listen to, you have time where
you're actually listening to music, but
you also have every TV show, every
movie, just when you're walking around
the supermarket, there's music playing.
When you're walking around any shop,
there's there's music playing. When
you're around at your friend's house,
they're playing music. You are
constantly bombarded with music. And you
re-listen to or like almost none of it.
If I give you 100 different artists to
listen to, how many would you actually
go back and re-listen to? Like, one,
two, three, maybe five? So, the vast
majority of music that you hear is just
passive. Like,
you don't even really hear it because
you don't like it that much. And I have
to accept that the majority of people
who listen to what I've made are just
they're not going to really dislike it.
They're just not really going to vibe
with it and probably never listen to it
again. And I think that's okay. I That
has to be okay. And hopefully, there's a
tiny little minority of people out there
who actually like it and maybe give it
one or two listens. That's That's really
all I can hope for. But, it is scary to
put your art out there for the world to
judge because
they're probably not going to like it.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, now I'm at a point where I I three
songs that I'm actually kind of happy
with. Like I've arranged them
and I've written them so that they feel
like kind of finished songs. And my
intuition is to just like export them
and slap them on Spotify and call this
project done. But we're actually only
halfway because these songs need to be
mixed and mastered so that they actually
sound good when you listen to them.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So this is where my knowledge just
abruptly
runs out because I have never mixed or
mastered a song because well, I've never
released anything, right? So I've always
just got to this stage and then kind of
just left it there. From what I
understand, this is a key part of being
your own bedroom producer and actually
releasing your tracks.
Essentially, what we're trying to do
here is to is to play with volume. Um
volume in various different ways off the
track to make it sound pleasing on
multiple different speakers. So laptops,
phones, massive surround sounds, huge
speakers, tiny speakers, crappy
speakers, expensive speakers. The way we
do that is when we manipulate volume. So
we can So if we mix a track, I can
actually turn down the volume off the
guitar and the bass and turn up the
volume of different things. So that's
getting the basic balance off the track
right. I think I should be able to do
that bit. But that's only really one
element off the off volume. So the next
thing we have to do is like EQ all the
tracks and the the master track as well,
which is basically adjusting the volume
of different frequencies to make it
sound pleasing and all fit together
nicely. And we also need to compress the
tracks. So that's adjusting the volume
in like the short term
to like squash the audio down.
>> [music]
>> Mixing and mastering these tracks was
hard. I really didn't even understand
what I was trying to achieve.
But, I gave it my best shot, and the
before and after test proved that I'd
gotten somewhere.
>> [music]
>> But, then came the most important
[music] stage of verification.
How does it sound on various different
speakers?
You know, how people will actually be
listening [music] to these tracks. We're
going to test it on this Google Home
speaker.
>> [music]
>> Place where I do most of my listening,
the car.
>> [music]
>> Oh, the bass doesn't sound right.
I'm trying to listen to it really loud,
and I'm I'm reaching for the volume dial
to turn it down. There's It's It's
irritating.
Practically unlistenable on the on a
phone.
That's bad. And I understand that my car
speakers and the phone [music] speaker
is crap anyway, but all our stuff sounds
okay on those speakers, [music] so it's
my track that's the problem. So, I went
back to the lab, comparing my mixes to
commercial music that I like, like the
Chili's, DJ Shadow, Bonobo, Massive
Attack,
and discovering where my mix had too
much or too little.
>> Yeah, this this part's going [music] to
take a while cuz
I'm only half done one song.
So right now I need to fix a bunch of
problems. [music]
Think after hours and hours and hours of
doing this, I'm starting [music] to
understand a little bit more about
mixing and mastering the tracks.
>> We're finally getting somewhere. This is
starting to sound good.
>> Finally and slowly over countless
iterations, [music]
the mix has started to sound more
polished. Still not as professional as
commercial [music] masters,
but way better than when I started. All
right, I've been excited about doing
this for a while.
Export.
That's right. That's what I'm talking
about. So I am done. I have
written, produced, mixed and mastered
three tracks. And by the time you're
watching this, they will be on Spotify,
Apple Music, iTunes, YouTube Music and
all the rest.
So I had to pick an artist name. I
couldn't come up with anything. I wanted
to just go for Mike Boyd. Someone
already has that and apparently it's bad
chat to have duplicate names on Spotify
[music] and things like that. So I went
for the name Micro Boyd, all one word.
That was my name at high school because
well, I'm short and my second name's
Boyd.
So Micro Boyd, search [music] it on
Spotify, iTunes, Apple Music, YouTube
Music, all the rest. Thank you very much
for watching and I'll see you all next
[music] time. Peace.
>> [music]
[music]